<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Biological Data Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Biological Data Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/syllabus/</guid>
      <description> Syllabus    Date Module Topics Read Code Homework   Week 1 home Course design, goals, introduction, and setup         MODULE 1: an introduction to computing in R       Week 2   git/GitHub      Week 3  An introduction to R and R markdown      Week 4  Visualization basics          MODULE 2: host-virus associations       Week 5 bug_report An intro to VIRION and strings      Week 6 bug_report Data manipulation (base + plyr/dplyr)         MODULE 3: ecological simulation       Week 7  Loops and apply      Week 8  `List` objects      Week 9  Probabilistic processes         MODULE 4: making and evaluating models       Week 10 my_location Working with APIs      Week 11 my_location Statistical modeling      Week 12 my_location Making informed models + model performance      Week 13  Making your code readable, clean, and reproducible         FINAL PROJECTS      Week 14 school Final Project presentations        </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Biol-599 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to R and R markdown</title>
      <link>/code/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/basics/</guid>
      <description>What is R and why should I use it? R is a statistical programming language that has quickly become the standard language for ecologists, and to some extent, biologists. This does not mean that you have to use it. I hope that many of the skills you learn in this course in terms of how to program are transferable across languages.
 R basics Variables Variables are defined as objects in R that can take on different attributes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to visualization in R</title>
      <link>/code/rplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/rplot/</guid>
      <description>Why is data visualization important? exploratory data analysis Visualizations help identify interesting things about the data. This includes how the data are distributed, values that are outliers, and potential mistakes in data entry. Use visualization to essentially assure yourself of the quality of the data and identify potential issues.
 clear demonstration of results relative to tables or statistics Visualizations are often more compelling at showing relationships between variables (and interactions between variables) than tables of statistical tests, and show more information than simple mean and standard deviations which would be reported in a table.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <link>/read/docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/docker/</guid>
      <description>Install Docker (Community Edition, free &amp;amp; open source) for your laptop. (Mac, Windows, &amp;amp; Linux)
  Launch the Docker command line, and run: docker pull rocker/r-base to download the image we&amp;rsquo;ll be using in class. If either of these steps do not work for you, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, we should be able to fix any special cases in class.
  Debugging Docker Install MacOS Docker installation is pretty robust on MacOS now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geospatial Data &amp; Visualization</title>
      <link>/read/geospatial-orig/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/geospatial-orig/</guid>
      <description>Reading Our geospatial module is meant only as an introduction to geospatial data, an already-rich area in R that is in mid-Renaissance right now, just as tabular data was in the past few years since the introduction of dplyr and the rest of tidyverse.
GeoSpatial Textbook: Geocomputation with R (Lovelace, Nowosad, Muenchow)
 Chapter 1: Introduction  Basic Visualization tools Also read over the following vignettes:
 Static maps: tmap Vignette Interactive maps: mapview Vignette  Watch UPDATED   DataCamp now has a more modern course from Zev Ross, Spatial Analysis in R with sf and raster that more closely aligns with the tools we will be using in this module (matching the Geocomputation reading above).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to spatial data</title>
      <link>/read/spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/spatial/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Brunsdon and Comber (2020) Opening practice: supporting reproducibility and critical spatial data science. Journal of Geographical Systems https://doi.org/10.1007/s10109-020-00334-2
  Chapter 1: Introduction
  Introduction to APIs [Nice blog post]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to APIs</title>
      <link>/read/api/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/api/</guid>
      <description>Reading  https://medium.com/@traffordDataLab/querying-apis-in-r-39029b73d5f1
  https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/guidelines-for-good-visual-information-representations
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iteration</title>
      <link>/code/iteration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/iteration/</guid>
      <description>What is iteration? Iteration refers to the process of doing the same task to a bunch of different objects. Consider a toy example of the actions required by a cashier at a grocery store. They scan each item, where items can be different sizes/shapes/prices. This is an iterative task, as it uses the same motions (essentially) across a variety of different objects (groceries) which may vary in many ways, but have some commonalities (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iteration</title>
      <link>/read/iteration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/iteration/</guid>
      <description>Read   R for Data Science textbook on Iteration: [r4ds-21]
  Looping [SW carepntries]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lists</title>
      <link>/read/lists/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/lists/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Good background on list objects
  Decent primer on apply statements
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling probabilistic processes</title>
      <link>/read/probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/probability/</guid>
      <description>Read   Intro to probability distributions [cyclismo tutorial]
  SIR model tutorial [SIR]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modules</title>
      <link>/modules/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/modules/</guid>
      <description>Computing in R    Introduction to programming  In this module, we will focus on programming fundamentals, with applications to biological data. We will also introduce libraries like plyr and dplyr to go over how the tidyverse gang opts to do data manipulation.    Host-virus associations   VIRION  In this module, we will learn how to manipulate and visualize data, using the largest host-virus association database as a learning tool.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelization</title>
      <link>/read/parallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/parallel/</guid>
      <description>Readings  Burton, A. W. (1991). Parallel processing in large-scale simulation: motivation and methods. Computing &amp;amp; Control Engineering Journal, 2(2), 74-79.
 working with lists  Focus on the lists subsection [Advanced R]  parallel computing in R   Parallel computing in R [NCEAS tutorial]
  parallel package [blog post]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plyr and dplyr</title>
      <link>/read/dplyr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/dplyr/</guid>
      <description>RStudio Primers   Working with Data
  Isolating Data with dplyr
  Derive Information with dplyr
  Readings   dplyr basic verbs: filter, arrange, select, and mutate, [r4ds-5.1 - 5.5]
  group_by, summarize and friends [r4ds-5.6 - 5.7]
  Relational Data (*_join functions) r4ds-13.1 - 13.7
  Resources for continuous integration   Introduction [Travis-CI]
  Introduction [Github Actions]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policies</title>
      <link>/policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/policies/</guid>
      <description>Instructor | Tad Dallas Location | Jones 101 Times | T &amp;amp; TH 2:50pm - 4:05pm Drop-in hours | Th from 1:00pm - 2:40pm Prerequisites You should be generally numerically literate, and some prior programming experience will be helpful. Students new to programming might find Hands on Programming with R to be helpful. Students with significant experience in programming and statistical analysis should find themselves well prepared but should find plenty still to learn in each lesson.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>programming basics</title>
      <link>/read/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/basics/</guid>
      <description> Complete the Programming Basics Primer on RStudio Cloud.  Reading   Introduction [r4ds-27.1]
  R Markdown [r4ds-27.2]
  Code chunks [r4ds-27.4]
  Getting help in R  R&amp;rsquo;s Documentation Getting Help Guide 1.6: Getting Help  Reference   R Markdown Cheat Sheet
  R Markdown Reference Guide
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R plotting</title>
      <link>/read/rplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/rplot/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Introduction [Base plotting]
  Principles of data visualization [Intro to DS]
  Function writing resource  R for Data Science textbook: [r4ds-19]  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDMs and model performance</title>
      <link>/read/performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/performance/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Breiman, L. (2001). Statistical modeling: The two cultures (with comments and a rejoinder by the author). Statistical science, 16(3), 199-231.
  SDMs SDM intro
  Model performance and model comparison Norberg et al. 2020
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDMs and model performance</title>
      <link>/read/sdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/sdm/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Breiman, L. (2001). Statistical modeling: The two cultures (with comments and a rejoinder by the author). Statistical science, 16(3), 199-231.
  SDMs SDM intro
  Model performance and model comparison Norberg et al. 2020
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setup</title>
      <link>/read/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/setup/</guid>
      <description>Reading The syllabus
Other resources   Carey et al. (2019) Enhancing collaboration between ecologists and computer scientists: lessons learned and recommendations forward
  Dynamic ecology blog post on comments from EO Wilson and the role of theory and code in ecology
  A beginner&amp;rsquo;s guide to reproducible research paper
  Prerequisites
  Running R code
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical modeling</title>
      <link>/read/model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/model/</guid>
      <description>Reading Spatial visualization resources   Static maps: tmap Vignette
  Interactive maps: mapview Vignette
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Style</title>
      <link>/read/style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/style/</guid>
      <description>Read Code style</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The VIRION data</title>
      <link>/read/virion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/virion/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Introduction [The VIRION data]
  Read the opening sections of chapter 13 on Strings and working with Regular Expressions: Sections 14.1 - 14.3.
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools</title>
      <link>/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tools/</guid>
      <description>  GitHub     R    cloud Cloud computing     Docker               </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials</title>
      <link>/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>GitHub Almost everything we do will involve GitHub in some way. This tutorial will provide a brief introduction to our GitHub-based workflow and review common git patterns for resolving issues you may encounter in working collaboratively.
Travis-CI Continuous Integration (CI) is an important concept data science practice has largely adopted from software engineering, in which a suite of tests are run every time changes are committed (i.e. pushed to GitHub or other version control platform) to a project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Version control and the command line</title>
      <link>/read/git/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/git/</guid>
      <description>Reading for this week:  Ram 2013. Git can facilitate greater reproducibility and increased transparency in science. Source code for biology and medicine, 8(1), 1-8.
 Other resources   Git Setup: HappyGitWithR.com
  Introduction to GitHub: GitHub intro
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with strings</title>
      <link>/code/virion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/virion/</guid>
      <description>VERENA The Viral Emergence Research Initiative (VERENA) is a global consortium. Our goal is to curate the largest ecosystem of open data in viral ecology, and build tools to help predict which viruses could infect humans, which animals host them, and where they could someday emerge.
Learn more about the consortium here
 VIRION With over 3 million records, the Global Virome in One Network (VIRION) database is a living encyclopedia of vertebrate viruses - including the ones that pose the greatest threats to human health.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
