<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reproducible Research in R</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Reproducible Research in R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/syllabus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/syllabus/</guid>
      <description> Syllabus    Date Module Data Topics Read Homework   Week 1 home  Course design, goals, introduction, and setup         MODULE 1: an introduction to computing in R      Week 2    git/GitHub     Week 3   R and R markdown     Week 4   Visualization basics          MODULE 2: host-virus associations      Week 5   An intro to VIRION and strings     Week 6   Data manipulation (base + plyr/dplyr) + CI         MODULE 3: species distribution modeling      Week 7 my_location  Intro to APIs and spatial data     Week 8 my_location  Visualizing and modelling species occurrence data + Docker     Spring break  --- ---      Week 10 my_location  Making informed models + model performance         MODULE 4: ecological simulation      Week 11  satellite Intro to simulation, looping and apply     Week 12  satellite lists and parallelization     Week 13  satellite Probabilistic processes         FINAL PROJECTS     Week 14 &amp;amp; 15 school  Final Projects     Week 15 (GIVE ACTUAL DATE HERE) school  Final Projects DUE       </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Biol-599 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/code/w10_modeling/funlab/breimannotes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/w10_modeling/funlab/breimannotes/</guid>
      <description>Breiman &amp;lsquo;two cultures&amp;rsquo; Prediction To be able to predict what the responses are going to be to future input variables;
 Algorithmic modeling culture: the shape of that function(x) of the predictor variables is unknown, and we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t specify a form. Focus is on model validation by predictive accuracy.
 Information To extract some information about how nature is associating the response variables to the input variables
 Data modeling culture: values of parameters are estimated from data, assuming that there is some known function that links predictor and responses, where information is the main goal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker</title>
      <link>/read/docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/docker/</guid>
      <description>Install Docker (Community Edition, free &amp;amp; open source) for your laptop. (Mac, Windows, &amp;amp; Linux)
  Launch the Docker command line, and run: docker pull rocker/r-base to download the image we&amp;rsquo;ll be using in class. If either of these steps do not work for you, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, we should be able to fix any special cases in class.
  Debugging Docker Install MacOS Docker installation is pretty robust on MacOS now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geospatial Data &amp; Visualization</title>
      <link>/read/geospatial-orig/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/geospatial-orig/</guid>
      <description>Reading Our geospatial module is meant only as an introduction to geospatial data, an already-rich area in R that is in mid-Renaissance right now, just as tabular data was in the past few years since the introduction of dplyr and the rest of tidyverse.
GeoSpatial Textbook: Geocomputation with R (Lovelace, Nowosad, Muenchow)
 Chapter 1: Introduction  Basic Visualization tools Also read over the following vignettes:
 Static maps: tmap Vignette Interactive maps: mapview Vignette  Watch UPDATED   DataCamp now has a more modern course from Zev Ross, Spatial Analysis in R with sf and raster that more closely aligns with the tools we will be using in this module (matching the Geocomputation reading above).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Git Basics &amp; Importing Data</title>
      <link>/read/git/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/git/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Git Setup: HappyGitWithR.com
  Introduction to GitHub: GitHub intro
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to spatial data</title>
      <link>/read/spatial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/spatial/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Chapter 1: Introduction
  Introduction to APIs [Nice blog post]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Iteration</title>
      <link>/read/iteration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/iteration/</guid>
      <description>Read   R for Data Science textbook on Iteration: [r4ds-21]
  Looping [SW carepntries]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling probabilistic processes</title>
      <link>/read/probability/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/probability/</guid>
      <description>Read   Intro to probability distributions [cyclismo tutorial]
  SIR model tutorial [SIR
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modules</title>
      <link>/modules/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/modules/</guid>
      <description>Computing in R    Introduction to programming   We will focus on programming fundamentals, with application to biological data We will also introduce libraries like plyr and dplyr to go over how the tidyverse gang opts to do data manipulation.    Host-virus associations   VIRION   In this module, we will learn how to manipulate and visualize data, using the largest host-virus association database as a learning tool    Ecological Simulation  memory Simulated data In this module, we will discuss how to simulate biological dynamics to test theory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelization</title>
      <link>/read/parallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/parallel/</guid>
      <description>Readings working with lists  Focus on the lists subsection [Advanced R]  parallel computing in R   Parallel computing in R [NCEAS tutorial]
  parallel package [blog post]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plyr and dplyr</title>
      <link>/read/dplyr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/dplyr/</guid>
      <description>RStudio Primers   Working with Data
  Isolating Data with dplyr
  Derive Information with dplyr
  Readings   dplyr basic verbs: filter, arrange, select, and mutate, [r4ds-5.1 - 5.5]
  group_by, summarize and friends [r4ds-5.6 - 5.7]
  Relational Data (*_join functions) r4ds-13.1 - 13.7
  Resources for continuous integration   Introduction [Travis-CI]
  Introduction [Github Actions]
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policies</title>
      <link>/policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/policies/</guid>
      <description>Prerequisites You should be generally numerically literate, and some prior programming experience will be helpful. Students new to programming might find Hands on Programming with R to be helpful. Students with significant experience in programming and statistical analysis should find themselves well prepared but should find plenty still to learn in each lesson.
Instructional Methods As a flipped classroom, students are provided with either reading or video material that they are expected to view/read prior to class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>programming basics</title>
      <link>/read/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/basics/</guid>
      <description> Complete the Programming Basics Primer on RStudio Cloud.  Reading   Introduction [r4ds-27.1]
  R Markdown [r4ds-27.2]
  Code chunks [r4ds-27.4]
  Getting help in R  R&amp;rsquo;s Documentation Getting Help Guide 1.6: Getting Help  Reference   R Markdown Cheat Sheet
  R Markdown Reference Guide
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R plotting</title>
      <link>/read/rplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/rplot/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Introduction [Base plotting]
  Principles of data visualization [Intro to DS]
  Function writing resource  R for Data Science textbook: [r4ds-19]  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDMs and model performance</title>
      <link>/read/sdm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/sdm/</guid>
      <description>Reading   SDMs SDM intro
  Model performance Norberg et al. 2020
  Pay close attention to how the model performance was assessed in terms of accuracy, discrimination, calibration, and precision.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setup</title>
      <link>/read/setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/setup/</guid>
      <description>Read   Prerequisites
  An introduction to the text and course structure
  Running R code
  RStudio Cheat sheet (for reference)
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The VIRION data</title>
      <link>/read/virion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/read/virion/</guid>
      <description>Reading   Introduction [The VIRION data]
  Read the opening sections of chapter 13 on Strings and working with Regular Expressions: Sections 14.1 - 14.3.
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools</title>
      <link>/tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tools/</guid>
      <description>  GitHub     R    cloud Cloud computing     Docker               </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials</title>
      <link>/tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorials/</guid>
      <description>GitHub Almost everything we do will involve GitHub in some way. This tutorial will provide a brief introduction to our GitHub-based workflow and review common git patterns for resolving issues you may encounter in working collaboratively.
Travis-CI Continuous Integration (CI) is an important concept data science practice has largely adopted from software engineering, in which a suite of tests are run every time changes are committed (i.e. pushed to GitHub or other version control platform) to a project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to Reproducible Research in R</title>
      <link>/code/w1_background/lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/code/w1_background/lecture/</guid>
      <description>Reading for this week:  Munafò, M. R., Nosek, B. A., Bishop, D. V., Button, K. S., Chambers, C. D., Du Sert, N. P., … &amp;amp; Ioannidis, J. P. (2017). A manifesto for reproducible science. Nature human behaviour, 1(1), 1-9.
  Structure of the class Syllabus We will go over this the first day of class. The first week will be no recorded lectures, and then the second week we will dive into the course design of 1 recorded lecture and 1 discussion/deep dive/clarification lecture.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>